now let's see how the rob is fixing our
exception handling problems remember
there are two of those problems one of
the problems occurs because this divide
can be delayed and realize that r2 is
zero much much later while the add for
example can be quick and be done so if
you remember with tomasulo's algorithm
the ad would deposit the result to the
destination register of the ad long
before the divide had a chance to
determine that r2 is zero and that
really we should have jumped to the
exception handler here and never
executed the add
so how does the rob help
well what we do is we treat the
exception just like any other result so
basically when we determine that r2 is
zero instead of producing a result for
r0 we mark the r0 in the rob as i mean
the result in the rob is now going to be
exception instead of a value when the
divide reaches the commit point at that
point the ad still hasn't committed and
everything before divide did so at that
point we can just do the kind of wait
for drain you know kind of flush
everything including the divide at this
point and then jump to the exception
handler and now we have a stable state
for the handler which is here basically
everything before the divide finished
the divide and everything after it
didn't finish which is exactly the state
that the divide by zero exception
handler should be seeing
similarly for a load that would here
have a page fault we would have the same
situation of when the page fault reaches
the commit we have committed everything
before the page vote and we haven't
committed the page fault itself or
anything after it so there is a very
nice resume point for the page fault
exception handler when we go back there
and load the page from the disk we can
jump back to the load or the store and
then start executing from here and
because nothing here has already
executed everything is fine the second
problem with exceptions that we had were
those phantom exceptions basically if we
predicted that the branch here is not
taken we would execute this divide and
maybe get the exception like divide by
zero and at the time when we get this
exception maybe the branch is still not
resolved so when we finally resolve the
branch it is too late because the divide
by zero has already been triggered so
how does an rob handle this well the
result of this instruction is now going
to be marked as exception in its rob
as the commit reaches the branch at that
point or before it depending on what
kind of branch
strategy we have we will figure out that
the branch has been mispredicted and
that we really wanted to jump to this
label here
at that point the divide and anything
over here is not committed basically we
haven't committed anything after the
branch so we can just cancel these
instructions they never reach commit and
thus the exception here is never
triggered so the idea with exception
handling is simply treat the exception
just as any other result and delay the
actual handling of exceptions until the
instruction that is triggering the
exception commits at that point we know
exactly what the resume point is for the
exception handler and we know that we
won't have any phantom exceptions
because
we would never reach the commit of this
divide unless this divide was on the
correct path for all the branches
basically if there was a misprediction
we would have cancelled this divide long
before it reaches the commit point